We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Today we hear about
dietary remedies
that encourage mosquitos
and ticks to find a meal elsewhere.
Are some people just more
attractive to mosquitos than others?
Apparently so,
as identical twins
are most likely
to be similarly tasty
compared to fraternal
twins who only share
50 percent of their DNA,
demonstrating an underlying genetic
component that can be sniffed out
by mosquitoes, although it’s
not clear if it’s because
some people smell better
or other people just smell worse.
We know pregnant women are twice
as attractive to malaria mosquitoes
and also that mosquitoes
are attracted to sweat.
Human sweat contains components
that are attractive to anthropophilic—
meaning human-loving—
mosquitoes.
The unique composition of human
sweat appears to explain
its tantalizing effect, though sweat
from some body parts
are evidently more
tantalizing than others.
Skin emanations
collected from armpits
were less attractive
compared to hands or feet.
Here’s the graph. They think
the difference may be caused
by deodorant residues,
since in a subsequent experiment,
volunteers were asked to avoid using
skincare products for five days,
and after that no
differences were detected.
The creepiest bit
of research I found was this.
The parasites that caused
the mosquito-borne disease malaria,
which kills hundreds
of thousands of people a year,
makes you more
attractive to, you guessed it,
the mosquitoes
that transmit malaria.
What better way for the parasites
to hitch from person-to-person.
Instead of leaving
it up to chance,
some parasites manipulate
their hosts in elaborate ways.
I’ve talked about how the toxoplasma
brain parasite draws mice
to the smell of cat urine
to get into cats’ brains,
or how about the rabies virus
concentrating in the saliva
while tapping into the Cujo
rage circuit in the brain.
There’s even a parasite that needs
to get from an ant to a bird;
so, it turns the ant’s belly bright
red to look like a ripe berry
and makes the ant
stick it up into
the air to confuse
fruit-eating bird.
Just like malaria
parasites making us
particularly tasty
to mosquitos.
Anything we can do to make
ourselves less tasty?
I’ve talked about the various
mosquito repellents
you could spray on your skin,
both synthetic and natural
mosquito repellents,
but is there
anything you can eat
or drink to make you
less of a target?
When you search the scientific
literature for diet and mosquitoes,
a lot of articles like this
pop up, on diets for mosquitoes,
like SkitoSnack for that artificial
blood meal replacement.
Feeding mice different
diets makes a difference,
but what about people?
One of the most
common anecdotes
is that vitamin B
complex supplements
protect against biting insects.
Other anecdotal remedies include
the taking of garlic, marmite,
vegemite, brewer’s yeast
tablets, and alcohol,
but you don’t know...
until you put it to the test.
How about a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of garlic as a mosquito repellant?
A belief in the ability of garlic
to repel insects seems
to be widespread;
so, researchers in Connecticut
decided to see if it were true.
They looked at the numbers
of mosquitoes
that did not feed
on the subjects,
the number of mosquito bites,
the weights of the mosquitoes
after feeding,
and the amount of blood
ingested were all determined
on people on and off garlic,
and the data did not
provide evidence
of significant
mosquito repellence.
No surprise given
that even if you slather
garlic oil on your skin,
within 30 minutes mosquitoes
don’t seem to care.
Eating garlic may,
however, help against ticks.
Because military personnel can
sometimes be at particularly high risk
for tick bites
and tick-borne diseases,
the Swedish military
conducted randomized
controlled double-blind trials
of garlic to prevent
tick bites among marines.
Fifty swallowed the equivalent
of about a clove a day of garlic,
and fifty took placebo pills;
then, they all switched.
And, there was a significant
reduction in tick bites
when consuming garlic
compared with placebo,
cutting the risk of tick bites
by about 20 percent.
Twenty percent is better than nothing,
but treating your clothing
with something like
permethrin has been shown
to be 100 percent effective
against deer ticks,
the vector of Lyme disease, and so,
that may be better than counting
on garlic bread to save you.
In our next story,
what happens when mosquitos
put on beer goggles?
An online survey of personal
mosquito-repellent strategies
unearthed all sorts
of strange stratagems
from cutting a tomato in half
and leaving it next to the bed,
to rubbing yourself with cigarette
butts soaked in alcohol.
You could also soak yourself
in alcohol with a gin and tonic,
cut down on sugar,
cut out meat, or bananas.
But what’s funny
is some say avoid bananas,
some say eat bananas
to stave off mosquitos,
and others say topically
rub them on your skin.
(I don’t even want to know about
what else you might do with them).
Eat bananas? Avoid bananas?
You don’t know...until
you put it to the test.
The impact of the consumption
of bananas
on attraction of a malaria
mosquito to humans.
Researchers in Wisconsin
randomized subjects to eat grapes
or bananas before testing what they
then tasted like to mosquitoes and...
the ingestion of bananas was strongly
associated with an increase
in the number of mosquito contacts
for hours after eating a banana,
translating to about
11 extra contacts
after 1 hour and 7 contacts
after 2 hours.
Meanwhile, the ingestion
of grapes had no effect.
Interestingly, it didn’t
seem to matter
how many bananas
you eat at once,
as eating three bananas
didn’t appear
to make people any tastier
than eating one.
Bottomline, after years
of repeat experiments,
they concluded that ingestion
of bananas, but not grapes,
resulted in a significantly higher
attraction of mosquitoes
for hours after
ingestion on average,
though some people did appear
to be immune to the banana effect.
What about that gin and tonic?
Some have suggested alcohol
will keep the bugs away;
others suggest we might
suffer more mosquito bites
after ingesting liquor.
Well, there’s only
one way to find out.
Drink some beer and put your arm
in a box with some mosquitoes.
The title of the study
gives it away.
Alcohol ingestion stimulates
mosquito attraction.
About 40 percent of the mosquitoes
landed on their arms
before drinking
a bottle of beer
compared to about
50 percent afterwards.
And it didn’t appear to have
anything to do with changes
in sweat production or skin
temperature after the booze.
It might just be something you
start exuding after you drink.
And so, it’s also not just because
you got bit a bunch of times
because you like blacked out
in an alley or something.
The researchers concluded that
since the percent of mosquitos
landing on volunteers significantly
increased after beer ingestion,
drinking alcohol stimulates
mosquito attraction.
But it could just be drinking beer,
not necessarily all alcohol.
And they only tested
one species of mosquito,
the one that transmits diseases like
dengue, zika, and yellow fever.
What about gauging human attractiveness
to malaria mosquitoes,
before and after volunteers
consumed either beer
(using 25 volunteers
and a total of 2500 mosquitoes)
or water as a control,
with 18 volunteers and only
about 1800 mosquitoes. And..?
Water consumption had no effect,
but beer consumption increased
the attractiveness of the volunteers.
It’s like the mosquitos
put on beer goggles.
Beer consumption increases
human attractiveness.
To date, bananas and beer
are the only dietary components
that have been shown
to increase mosquito attraction.
OK, but we want to repel
mosquitos, not attract them.
What about testing
B vitamins
as a home remedy
against mosquitoes?
B vitamins are often
recommended in the popular media
as a systemic repellent against
mosquitoes, especially on the web.
The first studies date
back over a half century.
They gave people doses
of vitamins B1 and B6,
yet in a series of subsequent
tests the mosquitoes
probed avidly
and bit promptly.
They only tested
the vitamins on four people,
but the vitamins
appeared so useless,
they didn’t think
it worth repeating
the experiments in view
of the obvious lack
of repellency
of these vitamins.
We believe, the researchers
wrote, that we have disproved
the notions that vitamins taken
orally act as mosquito repellents.
But they only tested
vitamins B1 and B6.
What about B-2, B-3,
B-5, B-9, B12?
You don’t know...until
you put it to the test.
Vitamin B complex supplements
are not effective as repellents,
but these studies were limited
by the use of very
few human subjects,
only 1 species of mosquito,
and a limited number of B vitamins.
So, researchers decided to put
it to rest once and for all.
B-1, B-2, B-3, B-5, B-6, B-7,
also known as biotin, B-9, B12.
They also just tried
a mega-dose of thiamine, B1,
which is rumored to be the most
effective B and...nothing.
No effect of vitamin B
supplementation.
Any of them.
I mean it would be nice
to have an effective
oral insect repellent.
Unfortunately, vitamin B1
has been proved to be ineffective.
And this includes so-called
mosquito repellent patches,
that supposedly deliver
B1 through the skin.
No protection
provided whatsoever.
Bottomline: Vitamin B1,
also known as thiamine,
is not a systemic
mosquito repellent in men.
They also tried smearing
it on people’s skin.
With failure after failure,
you start feeling bad
for the volunteers,
seated in a room
with their shirts off.
Then, they just release
100 suckers into the room.
Up to 96 bites per minute.
Just think how bad
it would have been
if they had had some
bananas and beer.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.